<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>AvaFrame</title>
    <link>https://avaframe.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on AvaFrame</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://avaframe.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - April 2023 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2023/</guid>
      <description>The &amp;lsquo;Happy Easter to Everyone&amp;rsquo; update:
As Easter vacation cut this month short, the amount work on the code concentrated on small issues, no major change.
One big chunk of our effort this month went into the Geoscientific Model Development paper about our dense flow com1DFA theory. Head over to GMD to follow the review and discussions.
Felix</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - March 2023 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2023/</guid>
      <description>Well, again: another month, some more releases:
But this time these are only minor releases with bugfixes. See infos here: release info 1.5.1 and release info 1.5.2.
We are still working on probability map generation.
We started to rework the glossary, focusing on topics that are relevant for our framework. We are not trying to replicate any &amp;lsquo;standard&amp;rsquo; glossary for the snow and avalanche field. It is meant to clarify what we are talking about and how we define certain keywords.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.5.2</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_5_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_5_2/</guid>
      <description>Today we released Version 1.5.2
This is a bugfix release:
FIX
Bugfix for parallel import on Windows Felix</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.5.1</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_5_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_5_1/</guid>
      <description>Today we released Version 1.5.1
This is a bugfix release:
FIX
For version 1.5 ANY simulation with com1DFA was marked as C (for changed) instead of D (for default), even in the case of no changes via local_ cfgs files. This is resolved now. Felix</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - February 2023 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2023/</guid>
      <description>Another month, another release:
This month&amp;rsquo;s release is version 1.5; please head over to the release info of version 1.5 to read more about it.
We are also preparing tools for probability map generation. Do not expect this to arrive soon, but it is planned for one of the next versions.
And on the admin side of things, we had a Steering Meeting, with a big focus on the next phase of AvaFrame.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.5</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_5/</guid>
      <description>Today we released Version 1.5
The parallel release. This adds parallel computation for com1DFA, meaning multiple simulations are run in parallel. For more information see our documentation. Be aware, there is a breaking change in case you call com1DFA functions directly: the calls to com1DFAMain changed; there is one less argument to give.
Add info about parallel computation in doc [com1DFA] rename s to travelLengthXY [ana4AIMEC] particle properties renaming: s -&amp;gt; travelLengthXY l -&amp;gt; travelLengthXYZ set kernelradius to cellsize for default settings [com1DFA] Add parallel computation of com1DFACore [com1DFA] Remove redundant argument from com1DFA functions [com1DFA] !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - January 2023 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjanuary2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjanuary2023/</guid>
      <description>Ok, so let this year begin!
This month&amp;rsquo;s main thing was the release of version 1.4; please head over to the release info of version 1.4 to read more about it.
Please note that we did not include an update to the AvaFrameConnector for QGis. We have bug reports of unexpected crashes on Windows, and we are trying to determine the cause.
The parallel computation is now included in the master branch and will end up in the next release.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.4</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_4/</guid>
      <description>Today we released Version 1.4
(and version 1.4.1; and this is totally not because I made the same mistake as before and forgot to add some files&amp;hellip;)
Version 1.4
This version adds a new computiational module com5GlideSnow for glide snow avalanches, based on com1DFA. It also adds an (untested) wetSnow friction type to com1DFA and gives an indication about the used parameterset in the simulation names of com1DFA.
ENHANCEMENTS
Glide snow [com5GlideSnow] GlideSnow run script glide snow standard tests SphKernelRadius setting option [com1DFA] Wet snow friction type [com1DFA] Wet snow standard tests Docu paragraph for wetSnow Remove unused location option in addColorBar [out3Plot] Add avalanche coordinate system to particle properties [ana3AIMEC] Triangular initialization method [com1DFA] Indicator of default/changed to simulationname and report [com1DFA] #780 Adds D/C to indicate default/changed parameter set in simulation name Also adds info and changed parameters to report New workflow com1DFA: com1DFAPreprocess com1DFAMain com1DFAPostprocess Add the dam tool [com1DFA] Update com1DFA dam documentation Add reference simulation to contour plot Add contour plot to aimec Split cython files [com1DFA] Add filtering for greater or smaller than Add resDF to be saved for com1DFA results that can be used for statistical analysis [com1DFA] Match code to the description in the theory paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publication summary 2022</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/publications2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/publications2022/</guid>
      <description>Here is an (incomplete) list of the 2022 publications related to AvaFrame. Maybe you might find some information that is of interest:
EGU 2022:
Tonnel, M., Wirbel, A., Oesterle, F., and Fischer, J.-T.: Are avalanche models correct? An uncertain view on convergence, EGU General Assembly 2022, Vienna, Austria, 23–27 May 2022, EGU22-7745, https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-egu22-7745, 2022.
Neuhauser, M., Neurauter, R., Tuermer, S., Gerstmayr, J., Adams, M., Koehler, A., and Fischer, J.-T.: Investigating the potential of GNSS-modules for inflow avalanche measurements, EGU General Assembly 2022, Vienna, Austria, 23–27 May 2022, EGU22-6416, https://doi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - December 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydecember2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydecember2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the last update of this year.
Another new tool was added to AvaFrame: calculating glide snow avalanches using the com1DFA module. This required significant internal additions like a new particle initialization method, adding bonds between particles and some other numerical functions. This, and the documentation, will end up in the next release, which is coming soon.
We are also working on indicating within the simulation names of com1DFA whether the default parameters were used or something was changed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - November 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynovember2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynovember2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the November 2022 update.
This month brought a lot of internal improvements and fixes, apart from one topic:
The dense flow module com1dfa now contains the functionality of wall lines. These can be utilized to represent the effects of dams. However, please be aware of two things:
first: this is untested and should only be used for experimental purposes. second: the application is directional dams, not catching dams. You can learn more about it in our documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - October 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoctober2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoctober2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome the first (close to) winter update of October 2022.
The main thing this month was the release of version 1.3, please head over to the release info of version 1.3 to read more about it.
This meant a lot of work went into bug squashing, removal of minor niggles and improvement of the documentation.
Please be aware that the installation method for QGis changed significantly. The AvaFrameConnector now tries to install the python package automatically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.3</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_3/</guid>
      <description>Today we released Version 1.3
The main change is the change of logic for secondary release areas. This was done to be able to expose these functions in the AvaFrameConnecter. So it is now possible to include secondary release areas in dense flow simulations done via QGis. Please also make sure you read the new installation instructions.
ENHANCEMENTS
Change logic for secondary release areas: Check for release and secondary release shapefiles If only release available -&amp;gt; just run release If both release and secondary release are available -&amp;gt; run with secondary release UNLESS secRelArea = False ALL scenarios in release get the secondary release areas!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - September 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyseptember2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyseptember2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the September 2022 update.
This was the month of conferences: First was the International Mountain Conference on our door steps in Innsbruck. We had a session about Gravitational mass flow simulations for avalanches with a bunch of very interesting talks. Thanks again to everyone who contributed and visited. The program can be found here.
We also took this opportunity to hold the Scientific Meeting, discussing, among other things, the future direction AvaFrame takes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - August 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaugust2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaugust2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the August 2022 update.
This month saw us adding a rotational energy line test which can be used to to checks eg. for numerical grid independence, i.e. the computations lead to the same results irrespective of the grid orientation. This includes helper functions and test data, see test case avaBowl.
Again, in preparation for the upcoming release, we changed the logic for the secondary release areas. So far they had to be requested specifically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - July 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjuly2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjuly2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the July 2022 update.
This month, despite being one of the slow summer month, we speed up our computation. Some variable are only computed if they are actually requested, so for most simulations this leads to faster compute times.
In preparation for a bigger overhaul of the AvaFrameConnector (QGis) we started adding helper functions that are used by the connector. These functions contain stuff like layer renaming and similar stuff that makes handling the result a bit easier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.2</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_2/</guid>
      <description>Today we released Version 1.2
The main changes are the automatic split point generation and optional computation of fields inside the calculation loop. Furthermore, renaming functions used for the QGis AvaFrameconnector are included.
ENHANCEMENTS
Add function for renaming simulations, i.e. adding info to the simName. Used for AvaFrameConnector Split cfgUtils: Utils contain all reading and writing; cfghandling has functions that do something with the cfgInfos Make computation of ppr, pta, P, TA and pke optional within the calculation loop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - June 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjun2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjun2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the June 2022 update.
This seems to be a recurring update lately: we are nearly at a rate of one release per month (this makes my life in regards to these monthly updates a lot easier&amp;hellip;).
To know what went on, head over to the release info of version 1.2.
So we recommend you update your installations, you will find the instructions at our documentation at the end of the installation instructions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - May 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymay2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymay2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the May 2022 update.
Bevor you keep reading here, head over to the release info of version 1.1 to get all changes that went into it. These changes are basically what we mainly worked on during this month.
However, two additional bits went on:
the ongoing writing of peer-reviewed papers and in relation to that, the EGU 2022 took place. The following contributions are related to AvaFrame: Tonnel, M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.1</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_1/</guid>
      <description>Today we released Version 1.1
The benchmark and thickness release. There are two main changes:
The benchmarks (i.e. reference results) are updated and originate from com1DFA now. Previously these were produced by com1DFAOrig. All references to depth are now switched to thickness. This is done to be more consistent and precise. It also means result types switch from pfd / fd (peak flow depth / flow depth) to pft / ft (peak flow thickness / flow thickness).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release Version 1.0</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_0/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version1_0/</guid>
      <description>So this is a big one:
On April 6. we released Version 1.0!
As you might guess, this is very exciting for us, but what does this mean?
First of all, you can find all changes in our documentation release notes. As one might expect with a first full release, the list is long!
Version 1.0 means we can partly fulfil a vital topic of our mission, namely the replicating &amp;hellip; current simulation procedures&amp;hellip; part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - April 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the April 2022 update.
The info in here is a bit short&amp;hellip; This is because there&amp;rsquo;s a separate post about the main event this month: Version 1.0 is out!! Please head over there to get the full info.
Apart from this we worked on:
a few fixes regarding init files reworking a few AIMEC functions and calculating real areas a few minor bugs are fixed added various documentation bits, especially the installation instructions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - March 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the March 2022 update.
As you might have noticed from all the other posts, this month saw our 1st public workshop. In case you missed it, see the previous post for a link to its recording. Big thanks to all participants, it is nice to know the interest in our project! And also, a big thanks for all the feedback we got, it is always very much appreciated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recording 1st Public Workshop 8. March</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/recording1stworkshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/recording1stworkshop/</guid>
      <description>As promised, here is the link to the recording of our
1st public AvaFrame workshop which took place on the 8th of March at 11:00.
Link to Youtube
The example data set mentioned during the workshop can be found here: example data
If you want to contact us for more information see here: AvaFrame communications.
Your AvaFrame core team</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - February 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the second update of 2022.
We are still preparing for the upcoming release, so expect to see some release candidates being published:
We are preparing a difference report with a comparison between com1DFAOrig and com1DFA. In there we&amp;rsquo;ll look at different numerical and other investigations, among this is comparison for different particle seeds.
It is now possible to use a range option to vary thickness values
Remeshing of the DEMs is improved now: if the remeshing was already done in a previous simulation, remeshing is not redone, but taken from a saved DEM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Info 1st Public Workshop 8. March</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/info1stworkshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 20:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/info1stworkshop/</guid>
      <description>As already announced, here&amp;rsquo;s some more info about the
1st public AvaFrame workshop on 8th of March at 11:00 (Central European Time; UTC+1:00).
It takes place via a zoom meeting: ZOOMLINK (Login via browser is possible, no app installation necessary). The workshop will be held in English.
If you want to follow the hands on demo:
please prepare by following the installation instructions on our documentation: standard installation.
you can bring your own data if you want, but we will also provide test data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - January 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the January 2022 update.
Our focus this month was the preparation for our upcoming version 1.0 release. We finished the month by publishing the first release candidate. See github releases for a full changelog.
For the final release of version 1.0 we worked on a difference report, investigating our numerics and comparing it to com1DFAOrig.
We streamlined and improved the way release thickness is being set in the DFA module com1DFA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1st Public Workshop</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/announce1stworkshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/announce1stworkshop/</guid>
      <description>We are happy to announce our 1st public AvaFrame workshop.
You are invited to join us on
8. March at 11:00.
The workshop will be held online, details with links to all necessary information will be posted on this homepage. We will cover the basic usage of AvaFrame via the AvaFrame QGis Connector and give you some background information. So if you want to learn how to use AvaFrame or have questions about it, we look forward to your participation!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for abstracts IMC 2022</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/announceimc22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/announceimc22/</guid>
      <description>We cordially invite you to submit abstracts to our focus session about
Gravitational mass flow simulations for avalanches
at the International Mountain Conference 2022 in Innsbruck, Austria, on September 11-15.
The call for abstracts is currently open and will last until February 16. IMC 2022 will be held in a hybrid format, more info here: modes of participation.
We look forward to many fruitful discussions and exchanges!
Kind regards,
Jan-Thomas, Felix</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - December 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our last monthly update for 2021.
This month so a broad development across all modules:
A new module ana4Stats/probAna is available and is concerned with all things related to probability runs and it therefore includes a lot of tools for parameter variations as well. This lead to some general improvements regarding filtering and ordering of simulations, both before any simulations are run, as well as for sorting and filtering results for postprocessing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - November 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our monthly update for November.
There are some changes especially for those wanting to try and test AvaFrame:
the AvaFrame QGis Connector is now out of the experimental state, so it is easily installable via the QGis plugins manager. No more need to enable experimental plugins. See QGis plugin directory.
We had our first webinar with about 15 test users. This group is testing AvaFrame from an operational point of view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - October 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first winter edition of the monthly update!
This has been a month with a lot of internal development, but not much of it landed on the master branch just yet.
The topics we are tackling at the moment are:
investigation of the initial particle distribution, we are trying different options and check to see if there is a significant change in the results. Aim is to make this easier to reproduce and less arbitrary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - September 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyseptember2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyseptember2021/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re back from summer! And with some exciting news too!
Version 0.6, the QGis/pypi and testing - release, was published.
So what is included in this release?
The installation process was completely changed and (hopefully) made a lot easier for you:
installation of AvaFrame is now working via pypi, i.e. through pip install avaframe. the pip install is provided for Windows, Linux and MacOS for python versions &amp;gt; 3.6. Note that we did not test MacOS (anyone got a free Macbook lying around?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public prototype and monthly update</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/publicproto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 07:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/publicproto/</guid>
      <description>In case you wondered where your beloved monthly update is, it was delayed due to us working on a big announcement:
We released version 0.5, our so called public prototype.
So now why is this big? (Apart from being a project milestone, which you couldn&amp;rsquo;t care less about I guess)
This is the first release that is being tested for application in operational hazard mapping.
To achieve this, quite a few things changed:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monthly public meeting</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymeeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymeeting/</guid>
      <description>We invite you to join our first monthly public update meeting on
Tuesday, 15. June, 9:30
via this link: online meeting (bigbluebutton, i.e. in your browser).
These meetings are meant to allow you to see what is currently going on in our development and we invite you to give feedback or suggestions.
We start with a flash update in which everyone working on the project gives a quick (2min) overview about their current work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - May 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymay2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 17:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymay2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the May 2021 edition of our monthly update. Our main goal was the preparation for the switch of the dense flow model com1DFA from a C code to python (cython) code. This meant to check every little detail and difference that we found as well as:
updated the documentation for the new python com1DFAP: algorithm, workflow and description
updated the re-projection method of particles. Now particles are re-projected normal to the surface and not vertically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - April 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 17:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the April 2021 edition of our monthly update.
Apart from the release of version 0.3, we put a lot of effort into our python/cython dense flow avalanche module com1DFAPy, targeting a swap with com1DFA within the next month:
com1DFAPy now includes:
an additional particle initialisation method: the per depth method
the option to use secondary release areas. They are being triggered if particles enter the area of a secondary release area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release version 0.3</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_3/</guid>
      <description>We just released version 0.3 - The AIMEC and Windows release -
This release brings an AIMEC refactor, plenty of improvements related to the test cases and Windows capabilities. 3 new idealised/generic test case are included: flat plane, inclined slope and pyramid.
Com1DFAPy recieved a lot of advancement as well, e.g. parts of it are converted to cython to speed up computation times.
Documentation regarding our testing is included, see more at the testing page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - March 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 19:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the March 2021 edition of our monthly update.
One big focus this months was a refactor of our AIMEC routines. We realised that our functions were still too complex, so we decided to
split it into more atomic function to make it easier to access only certain parts of the AIMEC functionalities. make sure no special folder structure is needed anymore. add an option to compare results from two different com modules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - February 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 19:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2021/</guid>
      <description>A short month with a lot of progress! It went over so quickly, even this post missed the end of the month&amp;hellip;
The big focus this month was the implementation of our dense flow kernel (com1DFAPy) in python/cython. The aim is to replicate the results of our current com1DFA module to be able to swap them. This meant diving deep into every numerical/model detail, things like
artificial viscosity friction forces particle initialisation and many more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - January 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 19:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first instalment of our monthly update of 2021. This month we started getting into the nitty-gritty of our dense flow module&amp;rsquo;s numerical implementation:
To facilitate and improve our development we added new test cases. This time they are more geared towards testing specific numerical issues and more targeted issues, concentrating for now on the dense flow module com1DFAPy.
flat plane: a pile of sand (i.e. particles with coulomb friction) on a flat plane.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - December 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 20:19:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to this years last monthly update.
This month we concentrated on getting more tests into our repository. We now have included all 6 realistic topographies with release areas and benchmark results in our test scripts. We also expanded our routine testing with pytest to more functions/modules. And those testing DEM&amp;rsquo;s, as well as the release areas, are freely available in the repository, see the data directory.
The availability of these test cases lead to the release of version 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release version 0.2</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_2/</guid>
      <description>We just released version 0.2 - The test data release -
Version 0.2 includes the first real world avalanches. It provides data for 6 avalanches, including topographies, release areas and benchmark results. To know more about our data sources, head over to our data sources documentation. The existing test cases also received some updates by including multiple release areas and multiple scenarios per avalanche.
All our standard test can be run by using runStandardTests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - November 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 20:19:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our next monthly update.
This month started with the exciting (at least for us :-) ) release of version 0.1. Head over to our github repository and our documentation to learn more about it (or read our last post).
With this release (and the rest of the month as well) we improved our documentation quite a lot. New getting started and installation pages should make it possible for you to get started (ha, who would have guessed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial release version 0.1</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_1/</guid>
      <description>We are very excited to be able to announce our initial release version 0.1!
This release is the result of several months of development, containing code from different contributors.
Disclaimer: please be aware that this is our initial release. So expect some (read: a lot of) rough edges!
You should be able to follow our quick start (only on Linux so far) and produce simulation results for dense flow avalanches. And yes, nice pictures are also included :-).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - October 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 20:19:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2020/</guid>
      <description>Winter has arrived here, so this is basically the first winter update:
This month focused on getting our code base ready for the upcoming release of version 0.1.
The documentation got a lot of attention with updates and improvements basically everywhere. Most notably we started to include installation and quick start sections for you to follow.
Testing took a big step forward. We expanded out standard tests, generated more benchmarks and created scripts to run these tests on demand as well as within our continuous integration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - September 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlysep2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 12:28:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlysep2020/</guid>
      <description>Winter is slowly creeping up on us, so here is the next AvaFrame update:
We heavily worked on the dense flow avalanche module com1DFA, bringing functionality from its native code over to python functions. Now there is the option to do parameter variations on friction parameters and release thickness automatically. Besides this new option, more and more simulation parameters can now be set in python.
Regarding the necessary executable for the com1DFA (dense flow) module: we discovered some discrepancy which we currently work on to resolve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - August 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaug2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 12:28:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaug2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to this months monthly update (try to say this really fast :-) ) :
The computational module for AlphaBeta is coming along nicely. We cleaned quite a lot of code and are starting the testing / comparing to reference results (Matthias is working on this).
Creation of idealised (test) topographies hit our public code base (see github). With these functions the creation of various types of topographies is a breeze (thanks Anna).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - July 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjul2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 09:49:32 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjul2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first installment of our monthly update on AvaFrame.
Every month we want to give you a quick overview of the progress on all things related to AvaFrame.
This month the project went into full force with 2 new team members: we welcome Anna Wirbel and Matthias Tonnel to the team! More info on the whole team will follow on this homepage.
The first (development) code is available on github</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project start</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/projectstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 16:04:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/projectstart/</guid>
      <description>The project AvaFrame has officially started with the 1st of June!
We updated the about page with our mission and aims. Information in German can be found here.
The first steering committee and scientific committee meetings already took place and our team members will start soon.
We will continuously keep you updated on this homepage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Position numerics CLOSED</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/positionnumericsclosed/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 17:13:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/positionnumericsclosed/</guid>
      <description>The following position:
Numerical developer/scientist for avalanche simulations
is CLOSED. Thank you for your applications, you should have recieved an email.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open position numerics</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/openpositionnumerics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/openpositionnumerics/</guid>
      <description>We currently seek to fill the following position
Numerical developer/scientist for avalanche simulations
For details see the pdf, if you have any further questions please use the matrix room (see contact) or details provided in the pdf.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/about/</guid>
      <description>AvaFrame is a cooperation between the Austrian Avalanche and Torrent Service (Wildbach- und Lawinenverbauung; WLV) and the Austrian Research Centre for Forests (Bundesforschungszentrum für Wald; BFW) within the Federal Ministry Republic of Austria: Agriculture, Regions and Tourism (BMLRT).
Our mission is to
Develop an open source framework (licensed with the European Union Public license (EUPL) ) for avalanche simulations which replicates and simplifies current simulation procedures and models at the WLV and make them accessible to the public domain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>We are using https://element.io/ / https://matrix.org/ for our communication.
You don’t have an element/matrix account: got to https://app.element.io/#/register -&amp;gt; Create Account
You can choose between using:
matrix.org, this is the default. your own or another infrastructure (universities, company, …). Setup via: Edit -&amp;gt; add your own homeserver. Note: It does not matter where your account originates, it works for the whole matrix environment.
Once you’re done, head to the next step:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reports</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/reports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/reports/</guid>
      <description>On this page we link to reports and publications that are related to AvaFrame, both produced by the project team or by cooperation partners.
Difference report for Version 1.0 -SATDifferenceReport_v1-
This report relates to our dense flow module and compares com1DFAOrig(SamosAT) results to com1DFA results. It can be found in the the assets of the version 1.0 release on Github, including supporting reports.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Team</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/team/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/team/</guid>
      <description>Core team
Anna WIRBEL (Scientist / Developer) ORCID
Felix OESTERLE (Project lead / Developer) ORCID
Jan-Thomas FISCHER (Scientific lead) ORCID
Previous members:
Matthias TONNEL (Scientist / Developer)
Amaury BÉLIÈRES-FRENDO (Trainee)
Oscar DICK (Trainee)
Operational Team Wildbach- und Lawinenverbaung
Matthias GRANIG, Christian TOLLINGER, Andreas HERBERT
Organisational committees:
Steering committee: Florian RUDOLF-MIKLAU (Head)
Scientific committee: Ingrid REIWEGER (Head)
External contributions
For a list of all code contributors, head over to the github contributors page</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
