<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>AvaFrame</title>
    <link>https://avaframe.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on AvaFrame</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 10:46:51 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://avaframe.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Initial release version 0.1</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_1/</guid>
      <description>We are very excited to be able to announce our initial release version 0.1!
This release is the result of several months of development, containing code from different contributors.
 Disclaimer: please be aware that this is our initial release. So expect some (read: a lot of) rough edges!
 You should be able to follow our quick start (only on Linux so far) and produce simulation results for dense flow avalanches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - October 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 20:19:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2020/</guid>
      <description>Winter has arrived here, so this is basically the first winter update:
This month focused on getting our code base ready for the upcoming release of version 0.1.
  The documentation got a lot of attention with updates and improvements basically everywhere. Most notably we started to include installation and quick start sections for you to follow.
  Testing took a big step forward. We expanded out standard tests, generated more benchmarks and created scripts to run these tests on demand as well as within our continuous integration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - September 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlysep2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 12:28:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlysep2020/</guid>
      <description>Winter is slowly creeping up on us, so here is the next AvaFrame update:
  We heavily worked on the dense flow avalanche module com1DFA, bringing functionality from its native code over to python functions. Now there is the option to do parameter variations on friction parameters and release thickness automatically. Besides this new option, more and more simulation parameters can now be set in python.
  Regarding the necessary executable for the com1DFA (dense flow) module: we discovered some discrepancy which we currently work on to resolve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - August 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaug2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 12:28:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaug2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to this months monthly update (try to say this really fast :-) ) :
  The computational module for AlphaBeta is coming along nicely. We cleaned quite a lot of code and are starting the testing / comparing to reference results (Matthias is working on this).
  Creation of idealised (test) topographies hit our public code base (see github). With these functions the creation of various types of topographies is a breeze (thanks Anna).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - July 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjul2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 09:49:32 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjul2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first installment of our monthly update on AvaFrame.
Every month we want to give you a quick overview of the progress on all things related to AvaFrame.
  This month the project went into full force with 2 new team members: we welcome Anna Wirbel and Matthias Tonnel to the team! More info on the whole team will follow on this homepage.
  The first (development) code is available on github</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project start</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/projectstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 16:04:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/projectstart/</guid>
      <description>The project AvaFrame has officially started with the 1st of June!
We updated the about page with our mission and aims. Information in German can be found here.
The first steering committee and scientific committee meetings already took place and our team members will start soon.
We will continuously keep you updated on this homepage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Position numerics CLOSED</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/positionnumericsclosed/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 17:13:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/positionnumericsclosed/</guid>
      <description>The following position:
Numerical developer/scientist for avalanche simulations
is CLOSED. Thank you for your applications, you should have recieved an email.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open position numerics</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/openpositionnumerics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/openpositionnumerics/</guid>
      <description>We currently seek to fill the following position
Numerical developer/scientist for avalanche simulations
For details see the pdf, if you have any further questions please use the matrix room (see contact) or details provided in the pdf.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/about/</guid>
      <description>AvaFrame is a cooperation between the Austrian Avalanche and Torrent Service (Wildbach- und Lawinenverbauung; WLV) and the Austrian Research Centre for Forests (Bundesforschungszentrum für Wald; BFW) within the Federal Ministry Republic of Austria: Agriculture, Regions and Tourism (BMLRT).
Our mission is to
 Develop an open source framework (licensed with the European Union Public license (EUPL) ) for avalanche simulations which replicates and simplifies current simulation procedures and models at the WLV and make them accessible to the public domain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>Visit our matrix room at: #public:matrix.avaframe.org
If you don&amp;rsquo;t have a matrix account yet, we suggest to use riot.im to create an account.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
