<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>AvaFrame</title>
    <link>https://avaframe.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on AvaFrame</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 20:46:51 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://avaframe.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Info 1st Public Workshop 8. March</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/info1stworkshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 20:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/info1stworkshop/</guid>
      <description>As already announced, here&amp;rsquo;s some more info about the
1st public AvaFrame workshop on 8th of March at 11:00 (Central European Time; UTC+1:00).
It takes place via a zoom meeting: ZOOMLINK (Login via browser is possible, no app installation necessary). The workshop will be held in English.
If you want to follow the hands on demo:
  please prepare by following the installation instructions on our documentation: standard installation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - January 2022 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2022/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the January 2022 update.
Our focus this month was the preparation for our upcoming version 1.0 release. We finished the month by publishing the first release candidate. See github releases for a full changelog.
  For the final release of version 1.0 we worked on a difference report, investigating our numerics and comparing it to com1DFAOrig.
  We streamlined and improved the way release thickness is being set in the DFA module com1DFA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1st Public Workshop</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/announce1stworkshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/announce1stworkshop/</guid>
      <description>We are happy to announce our 1st public AvaFrame workshop.
You are invited to join us on
8. March at 11:00.
The workshop will be held online, details with links to all necessary information will be posted on this homepage. We will cover the basic usage of AvaFrame via the AvaFrame QGis Connector and give you some background information. So if you want to learn how to use AvaFrame or have questions about it, we look forward to your participation!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for abstracts IMC 2022</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/announceimc22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/announceimc22/</guid>
      <description>We cordially invite you to submit abstracts to our focus session about
Gravitational mass flow simulations for avalanches
at the International Mountain Conference 2022 in Innsbruck, Austria, on September 11-15.
The call for abstracts is currently open and will last until February 16. IMC 2022 will be held in a hybrid format, more info here: modes of participation.
We look forward to many fruitful discussions and exchanges!
Kind regards,
Jan-Thomas, Felix</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - December 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our last monthly update for 2021.
This month so a broad development across all modules:
  A new module ana4Stats/probAna is available and is concerned with all things related to probability runs and it therefore includes a lot of tools for parameter variations as well. This lead to some general improvements regarding filtering and ordering of simulations, both before any simulations are run, as well as for sorting and filtering results for postprocessing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - November 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our monthly update for November.
There are some changes especially for those wanting to try and test AvaFrame:
  the AvaFrame QGis Connector is now out of the experimental state, so it is easily installable via the QGis plugins manager. No more need to enable experimental plugins. See QGis plugin directory.
  We had our first webinar with about 15 test users. This group is testing AvaFrame from an operational point of view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - October 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first winter edition of the monthly update!
This has been a month with a lot of internal development, but not much of it landed on the master branch just yet.
The topics we are tackling at the moment are:
  investigation of the initial particle distribution, we are trying different options and check to see if there is a significant change in the results. Aim is to make this easier to reproduce and less arbitrary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - September 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyseptember2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyseptember2021/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re back from summer! And with some exciting news too!
Version 0.6, the QGis/pypi and testing - release, was published.
So what is included in this release?
  The installation process was completely changed and (hopefully) made a lot easier for you:
 installation of AvaFrame is now working via pypi, i.e. through pip install avaframe. the pip install is provided for Windows, Linux and MacOS for python versions &amp;gt; 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public prototype and monthly update</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/publicproto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 07:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/publicproto/</guid>
      <description>In case you wondered where your beloved monthly update is, it was delayed due to us working on a big announcement:
We released version 0.5, our so called public prototype.
So now why is this big? (Apart from being a project milestone, which you couldn&amp;rsquo;t care less about I guess)
This is the first release that is being tested for application in operational hazard mapping.
To achieve this, quite a few things changed:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monthly public meeting</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymeeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymeeting/</guid>
      <description>We invite you to join our first monthly public update meeting on
Tuesday, 15. June, 9:30
via this link: online meeting (bigbluebutton, i.e. in your browser).
These meetings are meant to allow you to see what is currently going on in our development and we invite you to give feedback or suggestions.
We start with a flash update in which everyone working on the project gives a quick (2min) overview about their current work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - May 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymay2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 17:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymay2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the May 2021 edition of our monthly update. Our main goal was the preparation for the switch of the dense flow model com1DFA from a C code to python (cython) code. This meant to check every little detail and difference that we found as well as:
  updated the documentation for the new python com1DFAP: algorithm, workflow and description
  updated the re-projection method of particles. Now particles are re-projected normal to the surface and not vertically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - April 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 17:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyapr2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the April 2021 edition of our monthly update.
Apart from the release of version 0.3, we put a lot of effort into our python/cython dense flow avalanche module com1DFAPy, targeting a swap with com1DFA within the next month:
  com1DFAPy now includes:
  an additional particle initialisation method: the per depth method
  the option to use secondary release areas. They are being triggered if particles enter the area of a secondary release area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release version 0.3</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_3/</guid>
      <description>We just released version 0.3 - The AIMEC and Windows release -
This release brings an AIMEC refactor, plenty of improvements related to the test cases and Windows capabilities. 3 new idealised/generic test case are included: flat plane, inclined slope and pyramid.
Com1DFAPy recieved a lot of advancement as well, e.g. parts of it are converted to cython to speed up computation times.
Documentation regarding our testing is included, see more at the testing page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - March 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 19:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlymar2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the March 2021 edition of our monthly update.
  One big focus this months was a refactor of our AIMEC routines. We realised that our functions were still too complex, so we decided to
 split it into more atomic function to make it easier to access only certain parts of the AIMEC functionalities. make sure no special folder structure is needed anymore. add an option to compare results from two different com modules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - February 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 19:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyfeb2021/</guid>
      <description>A short month with a lot of progress! It went over so quickly, even this post missed the end of the month&amp;hellip;
  The big focus this month was the implementation of our dense flow kernel (com1DFAPy) in python/cython. The aim is to replicate the results of our current com1DFA module to be able to swap them. This meant diving deep into every numerical/model detail, things like
 artificial viscosity friction forces particle initialisation and many more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - January 2021 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 19:08:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjan2021/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first instalment of our monthly update of 2021. This month we started getting into the nitty-gritty of our dense flow module&amp;rsquo;s numerical implementation:
  To facilitate and improve our development we added new test cases. This time they are more geared towards testing specific numerical issues and more targeted issues, concentrating for now on the dense flow module com1DFAPy.
  flat plane: a pile of sand (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - December 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 20:19:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlydec2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to this years last monthly update.
  This month we concentrated on getting more tests into our repository. We now have included all 6 realistic topographies with release areas and benchmark results in our test scripts. We also expanded our routine testing with pytest to more functions/modules. And those testing DEM&amp;rsquo;s, as well as the release areas, are freely available in the repository, see the data directory.
  The availability of these test cases lead to the release of version 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release version 0.2</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_2/</guid>
      <description>We just released version 0.2 - The test data release -
Version 0.2 includes the first real world avalanches. It provides data for 6 avalanches, including topographies, release areas and benchmark results. To know more about our data sources, head over to our data sources documentation. The existing test cases also received some updates by including multiple release areas and multiple scenarios per avalanche.
All our standard test can be run by using runStandardTests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - November 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 20:19:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlynov2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our next monthly update.
  This month started with the exciting (at least for us :-) ) release of version 0.1. Head over to our github repository and our documentation to learn more about it (or read our last post).
  With this release (and the rest of the month as well) we improved our documentation quite a lot. New getting started and installation pages should make it possible for you to get started (ha, who would have guessed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial release version 0.1</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 10:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/version0_1/</guid>
      <description>We are very excited to be able to announce our initial release version 0.1!
This release is the result of several months of development, containing code from different contributors.
 Disclaimer: please be aware that this is our initial release. So expect some (read: a lot of) rough edges!
 You should be able to follow our quick start (only on Linux so far) and produce simulation results for dense flow avalanches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - October 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 20:19:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyoct2020/</guid>
      <description>Winter has arrived here, so this is basically the first winter update:
This month focused on getting our code base ready for the upcoming release of version 0.1.
  The documentation got a lot of attention with updates and improvements basically everywhere. Most notably we started to include installation and quick start sections for you to follow.
  Testing took a big step forward. We expanded out standard tests, generated more benchmarks and created scripts to run these tests on demand as well as within our continuous integration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - September 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlysep2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 12:28:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlysep2020/</guid>
      <description>Winter is slowly creeping up on us, so here is the next AvaFrame update:
  We heavily worked on the dense flow avalanche module com1DFA, bringing functionality from its native code over to python functions. Now there is the option to do parameter variations on friction parameters and release thickness automatically. Besides this new option, more and more simulation parameters can now be set in python.
  Regarding the necessary executable for the com1DFA (dense flow) module: we discovered some discrepancy which we currently work on to resolve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - August 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaug2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 12:28:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyaug2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to this months monthly update (try to say this really fast :-) ) :
  The computational module for AlphaBeta is coming along nicely. We cleaned quite a lot of code and are starting the testing / comparing to reference results (Matthias is working on this).
  Creation of idealised (test) topographies hit our public code base (see github). With these functions the creation of various types of topographies is a breeze (thanks Anna).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This month in AvaFrame - July 2020 edition</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjul2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 09:49:32 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/monthlyjul2020/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the first installment of our monthly update on AvaFrame.
Every month we want to give you a quick overview of the progress on all things related to AvaFrame.
  This month the project went into full force with 2 new team members: we welcome Anna Wirbel and Matthias Tonnel to the team! More info on the whole team will follow on this homepage.
  The first (development) code is available on github</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project start</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/projectstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 16:04:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/projectstart/</guid>
      <description>The project AvaFrame has officially started with the 1st of June!
We updated the about page with our mission and aims. Information in German can be found here.
The first steering committee and scientific committee meetings already took place and our team members will start soon.
We will continuously keep you updated on this homepage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Position numerics CLOSED</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/positionnumericsclosed/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 17:13:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/positionnumericsclosed/</guid>
      <description>The following position:
Numerical developer/scientist for avalanche simulations
is CLOSED. Thank you for your applications, you should have recieved an email.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open position numerics</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/posts/openpositionnumerics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/posts/openpositionnumerics/</guid>
      <description>We currently seek to fill the following position
Numerical developer/scientist for avalanche simulations
For details see the pdf, if you have any further questions please use the matrix room (see contact) or details provided in the pdf.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/about/</guid>
      <description>AvaFrame is a cooperation between the Austrian Avalanche and Torrent Service (Wildbach- und Lawinenverbauung; WLV) and the Austrian Research Centre for Forests (Bundesforschungszentrum für Wald; BFW) within the Federal Ministry Republic of Austria: Agriculture, Regions and Tourism (BMLRT).
Our mission is to
 Develop an open source framework (licensed with the European Union Public license (EUPL) ) for avalanche simulations which replicates and simplifies current simulation procedures and models at the WLV and make them accessible to the public domain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://avaframe.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:00:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://avaframe.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>We are using https://element.io/ / https://matrix.org/ for our communication.
You don’t have an acocunt, go to: https://app.element.io/#/register -&amp;gt; Create Account
You can choose between using:
 matrix.org, this is the default. your own or another infrastructure (universities, company, …). Setup via: Edit -&amp;gt; add your own homeserver.  Note: It does not matter where your account originates, it works for the whole matrix environment.
Once you’re done, head to the next step:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
